In Isabelle, we do that using a method called rule. So it's the first proof method that we
learn about. It's called rule. So basically, if we call, so if we just call, so for instance,
if we just call q, if we call this lemma one, then we can say, and the goal is p, then we
can just say, we can apply the method rule and give it as an argument, lemma one, and then
the goal becomes q. So in order for me to clarify that idea, let's try and do the same
proof as last time, but with backwards reasoning. So we have that goal again, the same file, sorry,
we will just, it's like that, there's something wrong with this C button, yeah, okay, so that's
the same lemma. And but instead of starting from the assumptions and reaching the goal,
we start from the goal and reach assumptions, how? So let's just say, we basically want
to show have not p, then we can just say apply rule. So our goal now is, as you can see, not p,
okay, so we can then transform that goal into something else, right, by just tracing the proof
that we did up there, but backwards. So what did you do to get that goal? We applied negation
introduction, okay, so rule, negation, introduction. So then we have two goals, as you can see, that we
need to prove that p implies some y, and p implies the negation of that y. And notice here, this
quantification, this is a quantification. So that means that we need to provide the other,
we provide rule with those two facts, approve them and then provide them to rule, or there's no way
you can prove it, okay, because you're going backwards here. So let's try and derive those
rules. I'll just derive them with sorry. So here we have, what did we say? So we needed p implies
y, and p implies not y for some y, and for some two y's, okay. So how can we do that? We can do that
by, firstly, this is the p implies y, I will just do this with a sorry now. So again, sorry here,
you're using it to just basically sketch down your proof, and then we want p implies q, this is
going to be assumption number one, okay. So now let's provide rule with those two facts that it needs
after it went backwards with, in the proof, all right. So in the proof state. So we provide it,
we provide rule with the two facts in the following way. So you say using, we need, I don't remember
if it was the negation first, or the other one first. So we needed the negation, I think first,
sorry, the p implies q first, and then p implies not q second. So that should be like that. So these
are the facts ordered like how rule wants them, and then rule was able to prove the remaining
goals with the two facts that we provided. So we tell it using assumption one and five,
for example, that's one way to do it. Another way to do it is, for example, by instantiating
the assumptions here. So if you remember, okay, let me just go back quickly to the board. So
remember here what we said about p, about rule, okay. Rule, if you have a theorem that says,
for example, q implies p, and then you have in your goal p, then it transforms the goal into q.
But if you apply it to a theorem that doesn't have any assumptions, then you already discharged
a goal. So we can turn negation introduction into a theorem without any assumptions by
merely giving it, as we did up there, some one as arguments, and assumption five, okay.
And then we have it, so let me just take it outside to just see what's, how does it look
like. So as you can see here, negation introduction, I wrote the same thing,
them negation with the assumptions, then you just have an op-p, otherwise you have the assumptions
and negation introduction, okay. So then that's one way, and then we can derive five again in
the same way, we just see what we go backwards. So we get, for example, we say, okay, five is an
implication, so whenever you have a connective in general, let me just write that, it's a
proof style thing, whenever you have, so I will just write some notes there, note, if you have a
goal with a connective, you want analyze that goal. So for example, break it down like negation,
like negation introduction, then you can just break it down into smaller digestible goals,
then you can use, I'll just call that connective, let's say op, then you can always use op
introduction, you can come up with a lemma called op introduction and try to use that for analyzing
the goal. So now let's go back there, so here we have, this is an implication there and we want
to analyze that, so we're going to use that implication introduction, so I will just say
use it by rule application introduction and then we can see what kind of goals appear to us and
then we can, from that you did use what more things you need. So you need to show that basically
not q holds, so you get that, you assume then you have that not q holds and then see later on how
can you prove that not q holds, but I will sorry it of course because we're going backwards in
this proof. Here I will again do the same thing, so for example, I would say using
four, so that should satisfy the only sub-goal that we had or you can also use,
you can do the same thing like what I did down there, you can do it that way or you can also just
another way to do it, the same from four, that's also the same thing, gives you the same
fact with you, so let's just see, so down with the goal, okay so you can have not q
which is four and then you want to prove that and then you apply rule implication introduction,
that goes one step back and then you're done. You can also do the following which is,
okay so now we have that goal, I'm sorry I'll remove like let's say we have, now we apply rule
and then that we have that goal and then we can apply rule a second time and they'll go even
backward more backward one more time in the goal. Here we're applying it with to a theorem that
doesn't have any assumptions which is not q, so then we have nothing remaining to prove
and then you can continue, okay so there is one more thing I wanted to say here which is
that you can also change the facts instead of saying using four or from four you can also say
then have five, so then does the same thing, so then takes the last fact and gives it to the
current fact, so you have the same, you have the same goal once you say then you then added four
and then add four as a fact and then you want to prove using it that. So I think that
like you can continue with the rest of that proof as an exercise on your own and it's just you do
the opposite of that proof basically with every step and then you sorry it and then you see how
it is. Let me just write some note there, so another note why use backward reasoning?
As I said earlier it is the same as forward reasoning right, but the difference is that
backwards reasoning allows you to debug the current proof goal. So if you don't know how
you can prove the current proof goal you can do backward reasoning and then analyze that goal
like for example if you have an implication you can do implication introduction and then see what
you need to prove or you can have negation introduction and then you will get two goals
like we did there, so it allows you to debug it so it's logically but it is logically the same
as forward reasoning there's nothing there's no other kind of logical reasoning in it it's
just that direction is different. So useful it's useful for top down development for top
down proof development. Okay so those are all the notes that I wanted to say so I think
I would recommend that you only if you have a pen and paper proof then you use forward reasoning
but if you if that proof for some reason doesn't work then you do the analysis the other way
around you do it backwards and then see where your proof breaks by getting the different
steps and you'll probably find that like you missed some some simple minute detail in one of the
steps. So I guess that's it for backwards